Samuel Wyllys Papers
Connecticut State Library
Samuel Wyllys papers
1663-1728
Connecticut State Library
Wyllys, Samuel
88 documents (1 volume)
The Samuel Wyllys Papers, 1668-1728, undated, are a group of 88 court documents that include 6 cases of witchcraft (42 documents), 12 cases concerning assault and battery, theft, adultery and other crimes (35 documents), and 11 other documents related to prayers of confession and petition, lists of freemen, poor relief, taxes, and titles to Indian land.
RG000_samuel_wyllys_papers
974.6 fW97
Biographical Note
Family
Samuel Wyllys was born in Fenny Compton, England in 1632 to George and Mary Wyllys. The family, including Samuel's half-sisters Amy and Hester, emigrated to New England in the early 1630s. Samuel's older half-brother George remained in England. By 1634 Samuel's father, George Wyllys, Sr. had been appointed an Assistant to the General Court of the Massachusetts Bay Colony. The family moved to Hartford in 1638. In Connecticut, George Wyllys, Sr. was elected to the Court of Assistants in 1639, Deputy Governor in 1641, and Governor in 1642. After his term as governor ended, George served as an Assistant to the General Court and chosen to be a Commissioner from Connecticut to the United Colonies of New England in 1643. George died in 1645.
Samuel graduated from Harvard College in 1653. He married Ruth Haynes, daughter of Connecticut's first governor, John Haynes, in 1654. The couple had one son, Hezekiah (b. 1672), who was Secretary of the Colony of Connecticut from 1712 to 1735, and three daughters, Ruth, Mary, Mehitable.
Ruth Wyllys died sometime before November 28, 1688, when Wyllys married his second wife, Mrs. Mary (Smith) Love at Berwick, Maine. Samuel Wyllys died on May 30, 1709 and was buried in Hartford's Ancient Burying Ground. There is no known portrait of Samuel Wyllys.
Government Service
Samuel was chosen magistrate of the General Court in 1654 and reelected each year. After Connecticut received its charter in 1662 he was elected as an Assistant and continued in that office until 1685. He often served as moderator when the Governor or Deputy Governor were not present. Financial distress from sugar plantations in Antigua led him to resign from the General Court in 1685. However, he returned to his position as Assistant from 1689 through 1692 and again in 1698.
Between 1658 and 1670 he sat on courts that tried witchcraft cases and as an Assistant in 1693 he was one of three judges that granted a stay to Mercy Disborough who was later acquitted. When Connecticut's charter arrived in Boston in September 1662, Wyllys was one of the men that brought it to Hartford. He served as a commissioner to the United Colonies of New England in 1661, 1662, 1664, and 1667. In 1676, during King Philip's War, he was authorized along with Major John Winthrop and Thomas Stanton to negotiate for a peace between the English and the Indians.
Charter Oak
According to tradition, when Joseph Wadsworth took action to prevent the surrender of the Charter to Sir Edmond Andros in early November 1687, he took it to Samuel Wyllys's home. At the suggestion of Wylly's wife, Wadsworth hid the Charter in a hollow of an oak tree and then put the dog kennel at the foot of the tree. The tree has come to be known as the Charter Oak.
Sources
Barbour, Lucius Barnes. Families of Early Hartford, Connecticut. Baltimore: Genealogical Publishing Co., Inc., 1977
See pp. 696-700 for information on the Wyllys family.
Shaw, Ernest R. Story and Legend of the Charter Oak Tree.. Farmington, Conn.:Heritage Trails, 1996.
Sibley, John Langdon. “Samuel Willis.” In Biographical Sketches of Graduates of Harvard University in Cambridge, Massachusetts. Volume I: 1642-1658, 323-325. Cambridge: Charles William Sever, University Bookstore, 1873.
See pp. 696-700 for information on the Wyllys family.
Talcott, Mary K. The Original Proprietors. Hartford: Society of the Descendants of the Founders of Hartford, Inc., 1986
See pp. 271-2.
Tomlinson, R. G. Witchcraft Trials of Connecticut. [s.l.]: R.G. Tomlinson, 1978
Scope and Content
The Samuel Wyllys Papers, 1668-1728, undated, are a group of 88 court documents that include 6 cases of witchcraft (42 documents), 12 cases concerning assault and battery, theft, adultery and other crimes (35 documents), and 11 other documents related to prayers of confession and petition, lists of freemen, poor relief, taxes, and titles to Indian land..
Related Material
, John Hay Library, Brown University.
In 1930, photostats of these documents were made for the Connecticut State Library and are now bound in a separate volume entitled Samuel Wyllys Collection Supplement, Depositions on Cases of Witchcraft Tried in Connecticut 1662-1693 [CSL Call Number Main Vault 974.6 fW97 Supp.]. In exchange, a photostat of the State Library’s volume of the Samuel Wyllys Papers was sent to Brown University.
Bibliography
Books
Barbour, Lucius Barnes. Families of Early Hartford, Connecticut. Baltimore: Genealogical Publishing Co., Inc. 1977.
[CSL call number HistRef F 104.H353 A22 1977] See pp. 696-700 for information on the Wyllys family.
Hall, David D. Witch-hunting in Seventeenth Century New England. Boston: Northeastern University Press, 1991.
[CSL call number BF 1575 .W62 1991]
Hinman, R. R. Catalogue of the Names of the First Puritan Settlers of the Colony of Connecticut. Hartford: Printed by E. Gleason, 1846.
[CSL call number SpecColl F 93 .H65] See pp. 108-9.
Report of the State Librarian to the Governor for the Two Years Ended September 30, 1908. Hartford: Published by the State, 1909.
[CSL call number ConnDoc St 292 1908]
Seymour, George Dudley. Captain Nathan Hale, Major John Palsgrave Wyllys: A Digressive History. New Haven: Privately Printed for the Author, 1933.
[CSL call number E 280 .H2 S512]
Talcott, Mark K. The Original Proprietors. Hartford: Descendants of the Founders of Hartford, Inc., 1986.
[CSL call number HistRef F 104 .H353 A28 1986] See pp. 271-2.
Tomlinson, R. G. Witchcraft Trials of Connecticut. [s.l]: R. G. Tomlinson, 1978.
[CSL call number BF 1576 .T65 1978] See pp. 67-8 for a brief overview of the Samuel Wyllys Papers.
“Trials for Witchcraft.” Hartford Times and Weekly Advertiser, August 8, 1820: 2.
The Wyllys Papers: Correspondence and Documents Chiefly of Descendants of Gov. George Wyllys of Connecticut, 1590-1796. Hartford: Connecticut Historical Society, 1924.
[CSL call number F 91 .C7 v. 21]
Index Terms
Persons:
Wyllys, Samuel
Subjects:
Trials (Assault and battery); Theft; Drunkeness (Criminal law); Trials -- Connecticut -- History -- 17th Century; Ordination -- Congregational churches; Freemen (American colonies); Public welfare; Taxation; East Haven (Conn.); New Haven (Conn.); Indian land transfers; Middletown (Conn.)
Document Types:
Testimonies; Reports; Judicial documents; Lists; Correspondence; Warrants; Title (property rights); Conveyances; Prayers; Religious texts
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Custodial History
After Samuel Wyllys's death, succeeding generations assumed responsibility for these papers. Three Wyllyses, each Secretary of the Colony or Secretary of the State for Connecticut in his turn, represent a ninety-eight year span in which the descendants of Samuel Wyllys had continuous custody of the papers. Samuel’s only son was Hezekiah Wyllys, who was Secretary of the Colony for 23 years (1712-35). Hezekiah’s son, George Wyllys, replaced his father in 1735, and served for 61 years (1735-1796).
George’s son, Samuel Wyllys, then replaced George in 1796 and was Secretary of the State for 14 years (1796 until his death in 1810). That Samuel had two brothers, William and Hezekiah, who allowed William Stone, editor of the Connecticut Mirror, to examine the papers relating to witchcraft. Transcripts of some documents appeared in the New York Commercial Advertiser, July 14 and 15, 1820; the New York Spectator, July 18, 1820; and The Hartford Times and Weekly Advertiser, August 8, 1820.
William Wyllys died January 18, 1826 and Hezekiah Wyllys on March 29, 1827. The documents accumulated by their ancestor, Samuel Wyllys, appear to have remained in the original Wyllys house until Hezekiah’s death. The house was then sold, and the papers went to Hezekiah’s daughter Amelia (Wyllys) Adams, wife of Ashur Adams of Charlestown, Massachusetts and, on her death (ca.1859) and Ashur’s (ca. 1861), to their children. In 1868, one of the children sold most of the documents to Nicholas Brown of Providence, Rhode Island.
Nicholas Brown passed the papers on to his son, Nicholas Brown III, and later they went to the son of Nicholas III, John Carter Brown. John’s widow, Mrs. Sophia Augusta Brown, on July 10, 1907 sold part of the papers to George Godard, Connecticut State Librarian.
The documents, of varying size, were then arranged, indexed, “preserved by the silk or Emery process,” and “substantially bound.” The resulting volume of Samuel Wyllys Papers is in the State Archives.
Alternative Form Available
Although a microfilm was made in 1954 by the Genealogical Society of Utah [Family History Library film 0003645], many of the items did not film well.
Links to digital images of the documents are provided in the "List of Documents" section.
List of Documents
- Witchcraft cases, circa 1662-1692
  - Case of Goodwife Seagar (Elizabeth Seager), circa 1662-1665; 2 manuscript documents
    - Testimony of Robert Sterne, circa 1662-1665
    - Testimony of Stephen Hart, Daniel Pratt and Josiah Wilard, circa 1662-1665
  - Case of Goody Ayers, circa 1662; 3 manuscript documents
    - Testimony of Goody Burr and Sammuel Burr, circa 1662
    - Testimony of Joseph Marsh, 1661 March 31
    - Testimony of the Inquest Committee, circa 1662
  - Case of Katherin Harrison (Katherine Harrison), 1668 June 29 - 1669 May 26; 12 manuscript documents
    - Testimony of John Welles, 1668 June 29
    - Testimony of Thomas Waples (Thomas Whaples), 1668 August 7
    - Testimony of Mary Olcott, 1668 August 8
    - Testimony of Richard Mountague (Richard Montague), 1668 August 13
    - Testimony of Rebecka Smith (Rebecca Smith), 1668 October 12
    - Testimony of William Warren about Katherine Harrison being a fortune teller, 1668 October 27
    - Testimony of William Warren about having his fortune told, 1668 October 30
    - Testimony of Samuel Martin, Sr., 1669 May 25
    - Testimony of Samuel Hurllbut (Samuel Hurlbut) and Alexander Keny (Alexander Keeny), 1669 May 26
    - Testimony of Samuel Hurlbut and Alaxander Keeny (Alexander Keeny), circa 1668-1669
    - Testimony of Eliazer Kimmerly (Eleazer Kimberly), circa 1668-1669
    - Testimony of Alis Wakely (Alice Wakely), circa 1668-1669
  - Case of Elizabeth Clawson (Elizabeth Clauson), 1692 June 6 - October 27; 7 manuscript documents
    - Bill of accusation, 1692 September 14
    - Testimony of Eliezer Slawson, 1692 June 6
    - Testimony of Mary Newman, 1692 June 30
    - Testimony of Thomas Penoir (Thomas Pennoyer), 1692 September 12
    - Testimony of Abram Adams and Jonath(an) Squire, 1692 September 15
    - Testimony of Sary Gold, An Wakman (Ann Wakeman), An Hardy (Ann Hardy) and Martha Henry, 1692 September 14-15
    - Testimony of Richard Holmes, 1692 October 27
  - Charges of Catherine Branch against Elizabeth Clawson, Mercy Disbrough and others, 1692 August 24 - September 19; 12 manuscript documents
    - Testimony of Cathoran Branch (Catherine Branch), 1692 September 19
    - Testimony of John Pettit, 1692 August 24
    - Testimony of Jonathan Bell about what Daniel Wescot told him, 1692 August 24
    - Testimony of Jonathan Bell on examinaton of Catherine Branch, 1692 August 25
    - Testimony of Jonathan Bell on Catherine Branch's claims against Goody Miller, circa 1692
    - Testimony of Joseph Garnsy (Joseph Garnsey), circa 1692
    - Testimony of Lidia Penoir (Lydia Pennoyer) about Catherine Branch's denials, 1692 August 24
    - Testimony of Lidia Penoir (Lydia Pennoyer) about what Abigail Wescot told her, 1692 August 24
    - Testimony of Joseph Bishop, 1692 August 24
    - Testimony of Samuell Blattchly (Samuel Blatchley), 1692 August 24
    - Testimony of Abigal Cross (Abigail Cross) about what Abigail Wescot told her, circa 1692
    - Testimony of Abigal Cross (Abigail Cross) and Nathaneel Cross (Nathaniel Cross), circa 1692
  - Case of Mercy Disbrough (Mercy Disbrow), 1691 - 1692 September 19; 6 manuscript documents
    - Bill of accusation, 1692 September 14
    - Indictment accusing Marcy Disborough (Mercy Disbrow), 1692 September 15
    - Testimony of John Wakeman, 1692 September 15
    - Testimony of John Barlow, 1692 September 19
    - Testimony of Hester Gromens (Esther Grumman), 1691, 1692 September 15
    - Bill of accusation against Widow Mary Staples, Mary and Hannah Harvey, 1692 September 15
- Cases of assault & battery, theft, adultery and other crimes, 1623-1728
  - Appeal of John Roberts, circa 1663-1728
  - Testimony of John Coultman in case of Goody Francis, circa 1663-1728
  - Inquest on John Biggs, 1674 January 28
    - Grand jury findings, 1674 January 28
    - Request for an inquest, 1674 January 28
  - Inquest on Indian named Poipee, 1705 August 20
  - Case of Capt. George Denison, 1663-1666; 3 manuscript documents
    - Testimony of John Divall, 1663 October 5, 1666 June 6
    - Testimony of Georg Tong (George Tong) & Peter Bletchford (Peter Blatchford), 1663 October 5, 1666 June 6
    - Testimony of Thwaite Strickland (Thwaite Strickland) & Aron Starke (Aaron Starke), 1663 October 5, 1666 June 6
  - Case of William Newman injuring Indian, 1665/6 March 24; 4 manuscript documents
    - Report to Gov. John Winthrop, 1665/6 March 24
    - Order by Gov. John Winthrop, 1665/6 March 24
    - Report of Committee, 1666 March 26
    - Testimony of Elizabeth Wettmor, 1666 March 26
  - Case of Robert Old & John Williams, 1672 September 5
    - Testimony of John French, 1672 September 5
  - Case of Indian (named Mesquamp), 1685 February 23
    - Testimony of Mary Wright, 1685 February 23
  - Case of William Cady, 1698 July 22, October 12, October 27
    - Search warrant for "callecos" in his possession, 1698 July 22
    - Testimony of William Pitkin & Zech Sandford, 1698 October 27
    - Testimony of John Hamlin, 1698 October 12
  - Case of Benjamin Denslow, 1728 May 13, 18
    - Accusation and bond, 1728 May 13, 18
  - Case of Israel Dibble & Deborah Bartlett, 1668/9 March 1 - 1669 May 26; 10 documents
    - Accusation, 1668/9 March 1
    - Warrant, 1668 March 1
    - Testimony of Samll Dible (Samuel Dibble) & Hephsiba Dible (Hephsibah Dibble), 1669 May 26
    - Testimony of Saumuell Dibell (Samuel Dibble) & Hephzibah Dibell (Hephsibah Dibble), who change their testimony, 1668/9 March 2
    - Testimony of Thomas Dible, circa 1668-1669
    - Testimony of Thomas Dible & Thomas Dible, Jr., 1669 May 26
    - Testimony of Jon(e) Dible, circa 1668-1669
    - Testimony of Mirriam Dibbell on her brother's wet stockings, 1669 May 26
    - Testimony of Meriam Deble on being in the orchard, 1669 May 26
    - Testimony of Thomas Deble, Jr., 1668/9 March 17
  - Case of William Moore, 1675 May 21; 2 documents
    - Testimony of Amos Richardson, 1675 May 21
    - Testimony of Mary Richardson, 1675 May 8
  - Case of John Rogers, 1675 May 26; 2 documents
    - Appeal of John Rogers, 1675 May 26
    - Testimony of Matthew Griswold, 1675 May
  - Case of John Fish, 1680 October 5, 7; 2 documents
    - Appeal by Samuel Willis, 1680 October 5
    - Testimony of Amos Richardson, 1680 October 7
  - Case of Abigail Bets (Abigail Betts) & John Slead (John Slade), 1672 July 26; 2 documents
    - Testimony of Nathaniel Boman, 1672 July 26
    - Testimony of Joseph Edward, 1672 July 26
- Miscellaneous papers, 1668-1711, undated
  - Prayers of confession and petition, undated
  - Dissenting congregation at Windsor, John Wareham's protest, 1668 October 9
  - General Court against ordination of Mr. Woodbridge, 1669
  - Names of freeman, Lyme, 1678 May 6
  - Names of freeman, undated
  - Provisions for poor frontier towns, 1697 June 30
  - Provisions for poor frontier towns, 1697 July 14
  - Taxes, East Haven, 1701 October 9
  - Taxes, New Haven, 1711
  - Title to Moheagan Land held by John Mason, undated
  - Conveyance of Indian land at Middletown, undated